"What Causes Wrinkles?"
How are wrinkles formed?
Their origin and nature is said
to be "notoriously complex,"
but current thinking
is that wrinkles occur
where fault lines
develop in aging skin.
The process has been compared
to an old leather glove,
made out of skin after all,
that develops creases
at the joints
due to repetitive stress.
In the face,
the repeated flexion
may be due
to facial expression.
An 8-year longitudinal study
found that you can predict
the pattern
of persistent wrinkles
by superimposing
upon your resting face
the expression lines,
temporary wrinkles,
that form when you smile.
Over time,
the skin folding
caused by
everyday facial expressions
etches the temporary grooves
into permanent wrinkles.
See how the smile lines
around the eyes at baseline
show up as permanent wrinkles
8 years later?
Given that wrinkles develop
from forehead furrows
and expression lines
from frowns and laughter,
one dermatology journal review
on aging skin
offered the tongue in
unwrinkled-cheek suggestion
of "Living alone to minimize
the use of facial expressions."
And while you're at it
you could
"live in space to avoid
the effects of gravity."
However, there is a way
to freeze parts of your face
into an expressionless mask:
Botox.
In fact, one contraindication
to getting Botox
is having a job that
"necessitates a wide range
of facial expressions."
It's never been
formally put to the test,
but there was a case report
of a pair of identical twins,
one of whom who spent
tens of thousands of dollars
getting Botox treatments across
multiple areas on her face
a few times each year
for 13 years.
Compared to her
non-regularly injected twin,
she ended up with
fewer imprinted facial lines.
A paper entitled
"Sleep Wrinkles"
tried to make the case
that wrinkles may result
from the skin distortion
from mechanical compression
sleeping on your side.
Of course, the primary author
also is a partner in a company
selling $160 quote-unquote
"wrinkle-fighting" pillows.
It turns out there does not
appear to be any correlation
between sleep position
preference
and the appearance of wrinkles.
Speaking of
questionable products,
what about topical adhesive
"anti-wrinkle" pads
you paste to your face at night?
Product claims include "look up
to 10-15 years younger,"
declaring a 70 percent reduction
in wrinkles.
But when actually
put to the test for a month
for crow's feet, forehead,
or between-the-eye wrinkles,
no objective benefits
were reported at all.
There did appear to be a placebo
effect in that subjectively,
the study participants felt
the wrinkles looked better,
but independent
blinded evaluations
by facial plastic surgeons
of before-and-after pictures
showed no significant change.
So what can we do
to prevent wrinkling?
Some of it is genetics.
For example, having lighter skin
color is a predisposing factor.
Among light skin tones,
Caucasian skin wrinkles more
readily than Asian skin,
for which aging
is more characterized
by pigmentation changes
such as freckles, blotchy
patches, and liver spots.
Among Asian skin types,
Chinese women tend to have
more wrinkles around their eyes
than Japanese women,
whereas Thai women
tend to wrinkle more
in the lower half
of their faces.
There are, however,
factors we have control over.
For example, drier skin has
also been found predictive
of more persistent wrinkling,
suggesting regular use
of skin moisturizers may help.
When it comes
to wrinkle formation,
it takes two to tango.
Wrinkles are formed
by repetitive creasing
of aged skin.
Kids can scrunch their faces
all they want
because the architecture
of their skin has yet to be
irreparably damaged,
and the lack of creasing
is why you don't have
wrinkles on your forearms
no matter how much sun
they've soaked up.
Rather than immobilizing
your face with Botox,
you can focus on preventing
the underlying structural damage
that makes your skin
susceptible.
This involves tobacco avoidance
and regular sun protection.
What about safeguarding
against other kinds of light?
From the Journal of Biomedical
Physics and Engineering:
"Can light emitted
from smartphone screens
and taking selfies cause
premature aging and wrinkles?"
Human skin cells bathed in
the light of iPhones and iPads
experienced an 80 to 90 percent
increase in free radicals,
compared to shielded
control cells,
suggesting electronic device
generated light
"may be harmful to skin."
Now, on one hand,
they positioned the screens
unrealistically close,
one centimeter,
resulting in about
10 times the irradiance
compared to a reading distance
of about a foot.
On the other hand,
the skin cells were only exposed
for an unrealistically
short time, only an hour.
The researchers called
for future studies
to evaluate the impact
of lower, longer doses
on skin outcomes
such as collagen deposition.